and this graph is only through 2021. It gets really, really ugly out towards 2030. And this graph sort of sums up what the problem is. The Democrats, they say, well, this isn't a big deal. We can just raise taxes a bit and close that gap, especially if we raise taxes on the rich. The Republicans say, hey, no, no, we've got a better idea. Why don't we lower both lines? Why don't we lower government spending and lower government taxes, and then we'll be on an even more favorable long-term deficit trajectory? And behind this powerful disagreement between how to close that gap, there's the worst kind of cynical party politics, the worst kind of insider baseball, lobbying, all of that stuff, but there's also this powerfully interesting, respectful disagreement between two fundamentally different economic philosophies. And I like to think, when I picture how Republicans see the economy, what I picture is just some amazingly well-engineered machine, some perfect machine. Unfortunately, I picture it made in Germany or Japan, but this amazing machine that's constantly scouring every bit of human endeavor and taking resources, money, labor, capital, machinery, away from the least productive parts and towards the more productive parts, and while this might cause temporary dislocation, what it does is it builds up the more productive areas and lets the less productive areas fade away and die, and as a result the whole system is so much more efficient, so much richer for everybody. And this view generally believes that there is a role for government, a small role, to set the rules so people aren't lying and cheating and hurting each other, maybe, you know, have a police force and a fire department and an army, but to have a very limited reach into the mechanisms of this machinery. And when I picture how Democrats and Democratic-leaning economists picture this economy, most Democratic economists are, you know, they're capitalists, they believe, yes, that's a good system a lot of the time. It's good to let markets move resources to their more productive use. But that system has tons of problems. Wealth piles up in the wrong places. Wealth is ripped away from people who shouldn't be called unproductive. That's not going to create an equitable, fair society. That machine doesn't care about the environment, about racism, about all these issues that make this life worse for all of us, and so the government does have a role to take resources from more productive uses, or from richer sources, and give them to other sources. And when you think about the economy through these two different lenses, you understand why this crisis is so hard to solve, because the worse the crisis gets, the higher the stakes are, the more each side thinks they know the answer and the other side is just going to ruin everything. And I can get really despairing. I've spent a lot of the last few years really depressed about this, until this year, I learned something that I felt really excited about. I feel like it's really good news, and it's so shocking, I don't like saying it, because I think people won't believe me. But here's what I learned. The American people, taken as a whole, when it comes to these issues, to fiscal issues, are moderate, pragmatic centrists. And I know that's hard to believe, that the American people But let me explain what I'm thinking. When you look at how the federal government spends money, so this is the battle right here, 55 percent, more than half, is on Social Security, Medicare, Medicaid, a few other health programs, 20 percent defense, 19 percent discretionary, and six percent interest. So when we're talking about cutting government spending, this is the pie we're talking about, and Americans overwhelmingly, and it doesn't matter what party they're in, overwhelmingly like that big 55 percent chunk. They like Social Security. They like Medicare. They even like Medicaid, even though that goes to the poor and indigent, which you might think would have less support. And they do not want it fundamentally touched, although the American people are remarkably comfortable, and Democrats roughly equal to Republicans, with some minor tweaks to make the system more stable. Social Security is fairly easy to fix. The rumors of its demise are always greatly exaggerated. So gradually raise Social Security retirement age, maybe only on people not yet born. Americans are about 50/50, whether they're Democrats or Republicans. Reduce Medicare for very wealthy seniors, seniors who make a lot of money. Don't even eliminate it. Just reduce it. People generally are comfortable with it, Democrats and Republicans. Raise medical health care contributions? Everyone hates that equally, but Republicans and Democrats hate that together. And so what this tells me is, when you look at the discussion of how to resolve our fiscal problems, we are not a nation that's powerfully divided on the major, major issue. We're comfortable with it needing some tweaks, but we want to keep it. We're not open to a discussion of eliminating it. Now there is one issue that is hyper-partisan, and where there is one party that is just spend, spend, spend, we don't care, spend some more, and that of course is Republicans when it comes to military defense spending. They way outweigh Democrats. The vast majority want to protect military defense spending. That's 20 percent of the budget, and that presents a more difficult issue. I should also note that the [discretionary] spending, which is about 19 percent of the budget, that is Democratic and Republican issues, so you do have welfare, food stamps, other programs that tend to be popular among Democrats, but you also have the farm bill and all sorts of Department of Interior inducements for oil drilling and other things, which tend to be popular among Republicans. Now when it comes to taxes, there is more disagreement. That's a more partisan area. You have Democrats overwhelmingly supportive of raising the income tax on people who make 250,000 dollars a year, Republicans sort of against it, although if you break it out by income, Republicans who make less than 75,000 dollars a year like this idea. So basically Republicans who make more than 250,000 dollars a year don't want to be taxed. Raising taxes on investment income, you also see about two thirds of Democrats but only one third of Republicans are comfortable with that idea. This brings up a really important point, which is that we tend in this country to talk about Democrats and Republicans and think there's this little group over there called independents that's, what, two percent? If you add Democrats, you add Republicans, you've got the American people. But that is not the case at all. And it has not been the case for most of modern American history. Roughly a third of Americans say that they are Democrats. Around a quarter say that they are Republicans. A tiny little sliver call themselves libertarians, or socialists, or some other small third party, and the largest block, 40 percent, say they're independents. So most Americans are not partisan, and most of the people in the independent camp fall somewhere in between, so even though we have tremendous overlap between the views on these fiscal issues of Democrats and Republicans, we have even more overlap when you add in the independents. Now we get to fight about all sorts of other issues. We get to hate each other on gun control and abortion and the environment, but on these fiscal issues, these important fiscal issues, we just are not anywhere nearly as divided as people say. And in fact, there's this other group of people who are not as divided as people might think, and that group is economists. I talk to a lot of economists, and back in the '70s and '80s it was ugly being an economist. You were in what they called the saltwater camp, meaning Harvard, Princeton, MIT, Stanford, Berkeley, or you were in the freshwater camp, University of Chicago, University of Rochester. You were a free market capitalist economist or you were a Keynesian liberal economist, and these people didn't go to each other's weddings, they snubbed each other at conferences. It's still ugly to this day, but in my experience, it is really, really hard to find an economist under 40 who still has that kind of way of seeing the world. The vast majority of economists -- it is so uncool to call yourself an ideologue of either camp. The phrase that you want, if you're a graduate student or a postdoc or you're a professor, a 38-year-old economics professor, is, "I'm an empiricist. I go by the data." And the data is very clear. None of these major theories have been completely successful. The 20th century, the last hundred years, is riddled with disastrous examples of times that one school or the other tried to explain the past or predict the future and just did an awful, awful job, so the economics profession has acquired some degree of modesty. They still are an awfully arrogant group of people, I will assure you, but they're now arrogant about their impartiality, and they, too, see a tremendous range of potential outcomes. And this nonpartisanship is something that exists, that has existed in secret in America for years and years and years. I've spent a lot of the fall talking to the three major organizations that survey American political attitudes: Pew Research, the University of Chicago's National Opinion Research Center, and the most important but the least known is the American National Election Studies group that is the world's longest, most respected poll of political attitudes. They've been doing it since 1948, and what they show consistently throughout is that it's almost impossible to find Americans who are consistent ideologically, who consistently support, "No we mustn't tax, and we must limit the size of government," or, "No, we must encourage government to play a larger role in redistribution and correcting the ills of capitalism." Those groups are very, very small. The vast majority of people, they pick and choose, they see compromise and they change over time when they hear a better argument or a worse argument. And that part of it has not changed. What has changed is how people respond to vague questions. If you ask people vague questions, like, "Do you think there should be more government or less government?" "Do you think government should" — especially if you use loaded language -- "Do you think the government should provide handouts?" Or, "Do you think the government should redistribute?" Then you can see radical partisan change. But when you get specific, when you actually ask about the actual taxing and spending issues under consideration, people are remarkably centrist, they're remarkably open to compromise. So what we have, then, when you think about the fiscal cliff, don't think of it as the American people fundamentally can't stand each other on these issues and that we must be ripped apart into two separate warring nations. Think of it as a tiny, tiny number of ancient economists and misrepresentative ideologues have captured the process. And they've captured the process through familiar ways, through a primary system which encourages that small group of people's voices, because that small group of people, the people who answer all yeses or all noes on those ideological questions, they might be small but every one of them has a blog, every one of them has been on Fox or MSNBC in the last week. Every one of them becomes a louder and louder voice, but they don't represent us. They don't represent what our views are. And that gets me back to the dollar, and it gets me back to reminding myself that we know this experience. We know what it's like to have these people on TV, in Congress, yelling about how the end of the world is coming if we don't adopt their view completely, because it's happened about the dollar ever since there's been a dollar. We had the battle between Jefferson and Hamilton. In 1913, we had this ugly battle over the Federal Reserve, when it was created, with vicious, angry arguments over how it would be constituted, and a general agreement that the way it was constituted was the worst possible compromise, a compromise guaranteed to destroy this valuable thing, this dollar, but then everyone agreeing, okay, so long as we're on the gold standard, it should be okay. The Fed can't mess it up so badly. But then we got off the gold standard for individuals during the Depression and we got off the gold standard as a source of international currency coordination during Richard Nixon's presidency. Each of those times, we were on the verge of complete collapse. And nothing happened at all. Throughout it all, the dollar has been one of the most long-standing, stable, reasonable currencies, and we all use it every single day, no matter what the people screaming about tell us, no matter how scared we're supposed to be. And this long-term fiscal picture that we're in right now, I think what is most maddening about it is, if Congress were simply able to show not that they agree with each other, not that they're able to come up with the best possible compromise, but that they are able to just begin the process towards compromise, we all instantly are better off. The fear is that the world is watching. The fear is that the longer we delay any solution, the more the world will look to the U.S. not as the bedrock of stability in the global economy, but as a place that can't resolve its own fights, and the longer we put that off, the more we make the world nervous, the higher interest rates are going to be, the quicker we're going to have to face a day of horrible calamity. And so just the act of compromise itself, and sustained, real compromise, would give us even more time, would allow both sides even longer to spread out the pain and reach even more compromise down the road. So I'm in the media. I feel like my job to make this happen is to help foster the things that seem to lead to compromise, to not talk about this in those vague and scary terms that do polarize us, but to just talk about it like what it is, not an existential crisis, not some battle between two fundamentally different religious views, but a math problem, a really solvable math problem, one where we're not all going to get what we want and one where, you know, there's going to be a little pain to spread around. But the more we address it as a practical concern, the sooner we can resolve it, and the more time we have to resolve it, paradoxically. Thank you. (Applause)
y esta gráfica es solo hasta 2021. Se pondrá muy, muy feo a partir de 2030. Y esta gráfica trata de resumir el problema. Los demócratas, dicen, bueno, no es una gran cosa. Podemos subir los impuestos un poco y cerramos la brecha, especialmente si subimos los de los ricos. Los republicanos dicen, no, no, tenemos una mejor idea. ¿Por qué no bajamos las dos líneas? ¿Por qué no bajamos el gasto del gobierno y bajamos los impuestos, y entonces estaremos en una trayectoria aún más favorable del déficit en el largo plazo? Y detrás de este poderoso desacuerdo sobre cómo cerrar la brecha, está la peor clase de cinismo de los partidos políticos, la peor clase de miembro del grupo, el lobby, toda la parafernalia, pero hay además intereses poderosos, respetuoso desacuerdo entre dos filosofías económicas fundamentalmente diferentes. Y me gusta pensar, cuando imagino cómo ven la economía los republicanos, imagino una asombrosa máquina bien diseñada, cierto tipo de perfección. Desafortunadamente, es un cuadro hecho en Alemania o Japón, pero esta máquina asombrosa que constantemente elimina todo el esfuerzo humano e insume los recursos, dinero, trabajo, capital, maquinaria, lejos de las zonas menos productivas y las lleva a las zonas más productivos, y aunque esto pueda causar perturbación temporal, lo que hace es construir unas áreas más productivas y dejar las menos productivas desvanecerse y morir, y como resultado todo el sistema es más eficiente, más rico para todos. Y esta visión generalmente cree que el papel del gobierno, un papel reducido, es poner las reglas para que las personas no mientan ni engañen, ni dañen unas a otras, quizá, tener departamentos de policía y bomberos y un ejército, pero un alcance muy limitado en los mecanismos de esa maquinaria. Y cuando imagino a los demócratas o a los economistas demócratas inclinarse en esa dirección, muchos economistas demócratas son, saben, capitalistas, creen, sí, que es un buen sistema la mayor parte del tiempo. Es bueno dejar que los mercados muevan los recursos a las áreas más productivas. Pero el sistema tienen muchísimos problemas. La riqueza se acumula en los lugares equivocados. La riqueza se le quita a personas que no deberían ser llamadas improductivas. Esto no creará una sociedad equitativa y justa. A la máquina no le importa el ambiente, el racismo, todos estos temas que hacen la vida peor para todos, y entonces el gobierno tiene el papel de tomar los recursos de usos más productivos, de las fuentes más ricas, para darlos a otras fuentes. Y cuando pensamos en la economía a través de estos dos lentes diferentes, uno entiende por qué es tan difícil de resolver esta crisis debido a que cuanto mayor es la crisis, mayores serán las apuestas, cuanto más, cada parte, crea que sabe la respuesta y que el otro lado va a arruinarlo todo. Y realmente me desespera. He pasado mucho tiempo en los últimos años deprimido por esto, hasta este año, en que me enteré de algo que me hizo entusiasmarme mucho. Siento que es una muy buena noticia, y es tan impactante, no me gusta decirlo, porque creo que la gente no me cree. Pero esto es lo que aprendí. Los estadounidenses, considerados en su conjunto, cuando se trata de estos temas, en cuestiones fiscales, son moderados, centristas pragmáticos. Y sé que es difícil de creer, que el pueblo estadounidense es moderado, centrista pragmático. Pero permítanme explicar a qué me refiero. Si analizamos cómo gasta dinero el gobierno federal, esta es la batalla aquí, el 55 %, más de la mitad, va a la seguridad social, Medicare, Medicaid, algunos otros programas de salud, el 20 % en defensa, el 19 % discrecional, y 6 % en intereses. Así que al hablar de cortar el gasto del gobierno, hablamos de esta tarta, y los estadounidenses abrumadoramente, sin importar de qué partido sean, mayoritariamente, les gusta este gran 55 %. Les gusta la seguridad social. Les gusta Medicare. Incluso Medicaid, a pesar de que va a los pobres y a los indigentes, que uno imaginaría que tendría menos apoyo. Y fundamentalmente no quieren tocarlo, aunque los estadounidenses están muy cómodos, y los demócratas aproximadamente igualan a los republicanos, en algunos ajustes menores para hacer el sistema más estable. La seguridad social es bastante fácil de ajustar. Los rumores de su desaparición son siempre muy exagerados. Gradualmente se aumenta la edad de jubilación, tal vez solo a personas que no han nacido aún. Los estadounidenses están 50/50, en si son demócratas o republicanos. Reducir Medicare para las personas mayores muy ricas, personas mayores que hacen mucho dinero. Incluso no eliminarlo. Solo reducirlo. Las personas generalmente están cómodas con eso, demócratas y republicanos. ¿Recaudar contribuciones para cuidado médico? Todo el mundo lo odia por igual, pero los republicanos y los demócratas lo odian juntos. Esto dice, cuando uno ve la discusión de cómo resolver nuestros problemas fiscales, que no somos una nación dividida profundamente respecto de los temas principales e importantes. Estamos cómodos con que se necesitan algunos ajustes, pero queremos mantenerlo. No estamos abiertos a la discusión de si eliminarlo. Ahora hay un tema que es muy partidista, y donde un partido solo quiere gastar, gastar, gastar, no nos importa, gastar más y son por supuesto los republicanos cuando se trata de gasto en defensa militar. Superan a los demócratas. La gran mayoría quiere proteger el gasto de defensa militar. Es el 20 % del presupuesto, y presenta un problema más difícil. También debo señalar que el gasto [discrecional], aproximadamente el 19 % del presupuesto, es tema de demócratas y republicanas, así que tienen bienestar, cupones de alimento, otros programas que tienden a ser populares entre los demócratas, pero también cuentas del Departamento del Interior y todo tipo de incentivos para la perforación de petróleo y otras cosas, que tienden a ser populares entre los republicanos. Ahora, en cuanto a impuestos, hay más desacuerdo. Es una zona más partidista. Tienen apoyo abrumador de los demócratas en elevar el impuesto sobre la renta a las personas que ganan USD 250 000 al año, los republicanos están en contra, aunque si los divides por ingresos, a los republicanos que ganan menos de USD 75 000 al año les gusta la idea. Pero, a los republicanos que ganan más de USD 250 000 al año no quieren más impuestos. Al aumentar los impuestos sobre la renta de la inversión, también se observa que cerca de dos tercios de los demócratas pero solo un tercio de los republicanos están cómodos con esa idea. Esto lleva a un punto realmente importante, que en este país tendemos a hablar de los demócratas y los republicanos y pensar que hay un pequeño grupo de así llamados independientes que es, ¿qué?, ¿2 %? Si sumamos a demócratas y republicanos, tenemos a los estadounidenses. Pero ese no es el caso en absoluto. Y no ha sido el caso durante la mayor parte de la historia estadounidense moderna. Aproximadamente un tercio de los estadounidenses dicen que son demócratas. Alrededor de una cuarta parte dice que son republicanos. Una pequeña astilla se llaman a sí mismos libertarios, o socialistas, o algún otro pequeño tercer partido, y el bloque más grande, 40 %, dice que es independiente. Por lo que la mayoría de los estadounidenses no es partidista, y la mayoría de la gente en el campo independiente cae en algún lugar en el medio, por lo que incluso aunque tenemos gran superposición entre las opiniones sobre estas cuestiones fiscales de demócratas y republicanos, tenemos superposición aún mayor al agregar a los independientes. Ahora tenemos que luchar sobre todo tipo de asuntos. Llegamos a odiarnos unos a otros sobre el control de armas y el aborto y el medio ambiente, pero en estas cuestiones fiscales, estas importantes cuestiones fiscales, simplemente no estamos tan divididos como la gente dice. Y, de hecho, existe este otro grupo de personas que no está tan dividido como la gente podría pensar, y es el grupo de economistas. He hablado con muchos economistas y por allá por los 70 y los 80 era feo ser economista. Estabas en lo que llamaban el campamento de agua salada, Harvard, Princeton, MIT, Stanford, Berkeley, o estabas en el campamento de agua dulce, Universidad de Chicago, Universidad de Rochester. Eras un economista capitalista de libre mercado o eras un economista liberal keynesiano, y estas personas no van a las bodas de los otros, se desairaban mutuamente en las conferencias. Es feo aún hoy en día, pero en mi experiencia, realmente, es realmente difícil encontrar un economista menor de 40 que todavía tenga esa forma de ver el mundo. La mayoría de los economistas... no es bueno llamarte un ideólogo de cualquier campo. La frase que quieres, si eres estudiante de postgrado o postdoctorado o profesor, un profesor de economía de 38 años dice: "Soy empirista. Me baso en datos". Y los datos están muy claros. Ninguna de estas teorías principales ha sido completamente exitosa. El siglo XX, los últimos cien años, está plagado de ejemplos desastrosos de veces en que una escuela u otra intentó explicar el pasado o predecir el futuro y acabo haciendo un trabajo horrible, horrible, por lo que la profesión de economista ha adquirido cierto grado de modestia. Todavía son un grupo de personas muy arrogantes, se lo aseguro, pero ahora son arrogantes sobre su imparcialidad, y también ven una enorme gama de posibles resultados. Y este apartidismo es algo que existe, ha existido en secreto en EE.UU. durante años y años y años. He pasado el otoño hablando con las tres organizaciones principales que encuestan las actitudes políticas estadounidenses: Pew Research, el centro de investigación de opinión de nacional de la Universidad de Chicago, y la más importante pero menos conocida, el grupo de Estudios Estadounidense de Elección Nacional que es la mayor encuesta de las actitudes políticas del mundo y la más respetada. Han estado haciéndola desde 1948, y lo que muestran consistentemente es que es casi imposible encontrar estadounidenses que concuerden ideológicamente, que apoyen constantemente, "No, no necesitamos impuestos, y debemos limitar el tamaño del gobierno", o, "No, debemos alentar al gobierno a desempeñar un papel mayor en la redistribución y corregir los males del capitalismo". Esos grupos son muy, muy pequeños. La gran mayoría de las personas deciden con cuidado, transigen y cambian con el tiempo al oír un mejor argumento o un argumento peor. Y eso no ha cambiado. Lo que ha cambiado es cómo las personas responden a preguntas vagas. Si uno hace preguntas vagas, como, "¿Cree que debería haber más gobierno o menos gobierno?" "Cree que el gobierno debe" —sobre todo si se usa un lenguaje tendencioso— "¿Cree que el gobierno debe dar cupones?" O, "¿Cree que el gobierno debe redistribuir?" Entonces se puede ver un cambio radical partidista. Pero al ser específicos, cuando realmente se pregunta sobre los impuestos reales y temas de gastos que se estén estudiando, las personas son notablemente centristas, son llamativamente abiertas a transigir. Así que lo que tenemos, entonces, cuando piensen en el abismo fiscal, no piensen como si los estadounidenses fundamentalmente no podemos soportarnos en estos temas y que debemos ser desgarrados en dos naciones beligerantes separadas. Piensen en ello como un diminuto, pequeño número de economistas antiguos y falaces ideólogos que han capturado el proceso. Y han capturado el proceso a través de formas familiares, a través de un sistema primario que fomenta ese pequeño grupo de voces de la gente, porque ese pequeño grupo de personas, la gente que responde a todo sí o a todo no sobre esas cuestiones ideológicas, puede ser poca, pero cada uno de ellos tiene un blog, cada uno de ellos ha estado en Fox o MSNBC en la última semana. Cada uno de ellos se convierte en una voz más y más fuerte, pero no nos representan. No representan nuestros puntos de vista. Y me lleva de vuelta al dólar, me lleva a acordarme que conocemos esta experiencia. Sabemos qué es tener a estas personas en la televisión, en el Congreso, vociferando que viene el fin del mundo si no adoptamos totalmente su punto de vista, porque es lo que pasa con el dólar desde que ha habido dólar. Tuvimos la batalla entre Jefferson y Hamilton. En 1913, tuvimos esta fea batalla sobre la Reserva Federal, cuando se creó con argumentos maliciosos, molestos, sobre cómo estaría constituida, y el acuerdo general de que lo que se constituyó fue el peor acuerdo posible, un compromiso garantizado para destruir esta cosa valiosa, este dólar, pero luego todo el mundo estuvo de acuerdo, está bien, mientras estamos en el estándar de oro, debe estar bien. La Fed no puede hacerlo tan mal. Pero luego nos salimos del estándar de oro para los individuos durante la Depresión y nos salimos del patrón oro como fuente de coordinación internacional de la moneda durante la presidencia de Richard Nixon. Cada vez, estábamos al borde del colapso total. Y no pasó nada en absoluto. A lo largo de todo, el dólar ha sido uno de las monedas más antiguas, estables y razonables, y todos lo usamos todos los días, no importa lo que la gente esté gritando, no importa lo asustados que se supone debemos estar. Y este panorama fiscal a largo plazo en que estamos en este momento, creo que lo más enloquecedor es que, si el Congreso simplemente pudiera mostrar que no están de acuerdo entre sí, que no son capaces de idear el mejor acuerdo posible, sino que son capaces de comenzar el proceso de llegar a un acuerdo, todos estaremos mejor al instante. El temor es que el mundo está mirando. El temor es que cuanto más retrasemos cualquier solución, el mundo verá a los EE.UU. no como la piedra angular de la estabilidad en la economía mundial, sino como un lugar que no puede resolver sus propias luchas, y cuanto más tiempo demoramos, más ponemos al mundo nervioso, las tasas de interés crecerán más, más rápido vamos a tener que afrontar un día de calamidad horrible. Y así, solo el acto de ceder en sí mismo y mantener un compromiso, nos daría aún más tiempo, permitiría a ambos lados diluir más el dolor y llegar a ceder más en el camino. Yo estoy en los medios. Siento que mi trabajo para que esto se dé, es ayudar a fomentar las cosas que parecen llevar al compromiso, no hablar de esto en esos términos vagos y atemorizantes que nos polarizan, sino solo hablar de esto como lo que es, no es una crisis existencial, no en una batalla entre dos visiones religiosas fundamentalmente diferentes, sino un problema de matemáticas, un problema de matemáticas realmente resoluble, uno donde no todos vamos a conseguir lo que queremos y aquél en el que habrá un poco de dolor esparcido por ahí. Pero cuanto más pronto lo afrontemos como un problema práctico, antes podremos resolverlo, y más tiempo tenemos para resolverlo, paradójicamente. Gracias. (Aplausos)